profiles in holography is brought to you
through the generous support of the
international holography fund for more
information visit their website at
holographyfund.org
this is Frank de Freitas and I would
like to welcome you to hollow talks
profiles in holography
this series of Internet broadcasts
focuses specifically on Art holography
and the artists who create the work
my guest for this installment is
Australian artist Amy rush I hope you
enjoy our informal chat and that you
return for all of the upcoming
broadcasts in the series and now here's
Amy Rush
[Music]
may I speak to Amy Rush please yes it's
me oh hello hello
I called a little earlier a few minutes
ago and then I got Anna Maria's other
number and she's out in San Francisco
yeah yes too but she told me to just
keep trying and somebody will pick up
and that's true someone did oh that's
great I was just waiting um I was
waiting at a sushi restaurant for
takeaway Sushi oh and they were taking a
really long time and I was like oh no
I'm gonna move spank
how is the time right now is it okay for
you or are you eating lunch it's good
it's perfect I don't want to come in
between your you and Sushi
it's okay it's okay I mean
I mean breakfast already and this issue
is like cold Sushi anyway okay it
doesn't matter at all I can I can wait
for my Sushi it can be my reward after I
speak with you okay good how are things
going with your installation
um well they're going okay I've had a
few
um difficulties like with the lights
because I bought all the lights from
Australia okay and I change the voltage
of them oh yes like I had to find the
right Transformers and like oh geez yeah
and also I had this other problem where
I um I wasn't allowed to bring my
Holograms in hand luggage
oh that's interesting yeah because they
were too big oh okay so some of them
actually broke which was really
cool Amy I know
it was really sad but but then something
good happened out of the whole thing
because
um I I spoke to the people in Germany
where
stereograms and they have offered to
reprint some of them for me oh that's
wonderful yeah so it kind of worked out
anyway and I'm getting new ones printed
too so it's even more exciting for me
now that's good now the Holograms that
broke were they on glass plates or are
they film and just the plexiglass or
something cracked no no they're they're
on glass plates
film laminated onto glass oh I see
um it's it's really hard to get it off
like I've done some tests and the film
kind of just evaporates but
um I've decided never ever to laminate
my my my
um my film ever again onto glass yeah
it's a shame that it had to take
something like this though to
make you make that decision yeah yeah
well I think it's kind of hard to carry
and it's kind of um really fragile and
you know if you just have them on on a
film and you roll them up or if you put
them you know you can show them without
the glass I think on the don't do it
anymore with class yeah I work on glass
plates oh yeah so you know you know that
they break you know it's horrible so
between Holograms breaking and being
stolen I don't have uh a lot of them are
going
to go
oh yeah really yeah what happened I had
a I had one stone from an actual Museum
one time I don't know how they ever got
out the door with one of them oh my God
that
that is a big compliment well I did at
the time but now that years have gone by
I'd rather have the Hologram back I
wonder where it is I I often wonder
where it is
so why don't you let the listeners know
you're on what's called A World Tour
that sounds pretty exciting yeah do you
have t-shirts made up with all the
cities that you're visiting or tell us
about the world tour
okay well
um it kind of started in Australia last
month I just finished my thesis so it's
kind of like a very big
um
uh reward as you might say and so in in
this exhibition
um we we started in Sydney and I had an
exhibition at um
at exhibition space okay and that was
really it was really wonderful because I
never had ever exhibited my Holograms in
Sydney Australia before
and that's where I um that's where I'm
born and where I lived and stuff like
this so okay it was really exciting to
show all my friends and my family all
the different works that I've been doing
over these years and it was really
amazing also because no I mean in in
Sydney Australia there's there's hardly
ever any hologram exhibitions oh isn't
that a shame yeah it is but um it was
kind of interesting because people just
came in and if you didn't show them the
work like to have a look at the work and
explain to them you know that you have
to look stand in front and move your
body and your eyes they would they would
just walk in and walk straight out again
without yeah
like they would just poke their head in
so I had to have my boyfriend come in I
mean standing in there the whole time
and you know explaining to the people I
just totally overwhelmed you know
they're like what what is this oh wow I
see it now I see it now come over here
look at this yeah I see it look
exciting you know to have these people
experience the medium of hologram
through my own work yes yeah yeah so I
was really pleased and you know there
was a lot of students that got to see it
as well and
well and asking like
where can we do this how can we do this
you know and you know just really
excited and enthusiastic about
everything
so it was good okay so that's where the
tour began
and then um like about one day after we
took the exhibition down we we came
straight to New York to the Center for
holographic Arts where I made some
Holograms in the past
you were a part of the Artisan residency
program as an or an intern or something
there oh yeah well I was an intern like
right at the beginning of my interest in
holography in 2003 so I stayed here for
about um six months and made my first
series of work
um yeah so it's amazing to be back here
because
um you know like I haven't been here for
maybe
um four years
see everybody that that was here and
that helped me at the beginning and the
people that like didn't really know what
I was doing since I came here and I get
to show them all the new stuff and so
really nice and
yeah I'm just setting it up like setting
up the show and it's going to open on
the 8th of
um the 8th of December yeah December
exactly and let me let the list
because you know that these shows get
archived so that anyone can listen to
people are still listening to shows that
were done 10 years ago so let me let the
listeners know that we're talking about
December 8th
2007.
because if someone's listening 10 years
from now it's going to be 2017. oh wow
you know so it's 2007. well hello out
there in the future
too so you move from you know you left
Australia which is summertime to come up
to New York City which is going into the
dead of winter
and to make things more extreme we're
actually going to Iceland oh my goodness
January what's with holography in
Iceland well I don't know if there's
much there's much happening in
holography in Iceland but um I believe
that Iceland would be the most ideal
country to display Holograms because
it's dark all the time and
interested in
Supernatural scenes like ghosts and they
have a lot of folklores and
um you know they have the Northern
Lights as well so they kind of have this
you know interest in life I guess too
and yeah so I think I think that they
might be my most excited audience that's
what I'm expecting wow yeah and how do
you put did you put this tour together
yourself yeah yeah I did I kind of
applied for some
um residencies and some
um asked some people that I knew that
have made that hosted holographic
exhibitions before okay yes I kind of
just like asked some people and kind of
you know um applied for some things and
then it kind of fitted together somehow
plug-in for Jonathan Ross as well
because then you'll be heading over to
England I imagine right yeah we're going
there in February and I think I so will
open like maybe on the 5th of February
in
London I never went to London before no
kidding no I've never been to London
either really yeah
why don't you tell the listeners about
the types of holograms that you've
created as far as the format of
holography that you prefer to work in
okay
um well the the thing that I really love
and the thing that um I I focused all my
Holograms in is the the transmission
white light hologram the rainbow
hologram
and so I first started making analog
analog Holograms rainbow Holograms from
um pulse Master copies I mean so pulse
Masters and then I made copies of them
on the on the table and yeah I just made
some of them were
two uh did you say two frames or two
Expo two explosives okay yeah double
exposure double explosive and then um
yeah so I did that and I was really
happy with the result of having because
it had a lot of depth in it and it was
also
um able to to capture real moments of
time what happens with that when you
walk past it one image sort of Fades
into another yeah yeah so the first one
I made was like this um this kind of
image of myself as a as a rainbow fairy
princess like winking winking so I might
it's like a double Expo
you know and when you go in front of it
I wink at you it kind of inspired from
the 80s porn Holograms that they were
making oh I haven't seen any of those
those are the kids kind of
um
I guess style or something that they did
you know these ones that where the girl
you see the girl undresses or something
like okay
yeah it's kind of I don't have any of
those in my collection oh I'm so happy
and yeah okay so then after I started
doing the analog Holograms
um I I was invited to the kaha m The
Academy of media arts where they had a
stereogram machine
and they they make eight seconds
um stereograms which is set at 8
25 frames okay of
um uh digital movie or digital still
images
um that are exposed next to each other
and they can create
movement like
it and sometimes you can make the depth
if you play with the camera like zooming
in or zooming out or something
and then after those the Sarah Graham I
also made um
oh okay two dot matrix printed ones that
they were digital ones as well and I
really liked the the way that they were
just so bright
you know if you're looking at them the
rainbow was almost reflected onto your
onto your face wow yeah yeah so that
those are the types of ones that I made
they're all the rainbow rainbow nature
do you have any
have any inflection holography at all
um no not really I was just totally
interested in the rainbow ones actually
you like the color right yeah well I
like I mean I like this idea of making
images inside it inside a rainbow
yeah so that was that was kind of the
whole thing with holography was that you
could make each
um
each piece of the film be every single
color all at once depending on the
viewer's position yes yeah and I can all
be programmed with the dot matrix
printer right
yeah well you can you can choose which
pixel is which color yeah and yeah then
that that kind of
um
makes makes all the colors yeah when you
go up and down and it's just because
you're using real colors
be
red green blue and all the ones in
between it's it's actually really really
bright and then that's how put onto film
right that's not a is that Adam's
telegraphy or is that on to film I don't
know it's on to film okay it's it's
pixel is exposed one by one in a kind of
a printer
who are some of the people you've done a
lot of collaborations right who who are
some of the people that you've
collaborated with on what projects
um well I usually uh collaborate with
whoever is
around the time like I'll received a lot
of help from the technical aspect
like all of my Holograms have been
collaborations in that in that way
because I've
all help from from people who are quite
experienced in the lab right yes in the
lab and
um but also like whenever I make a show
or an exhibition I have
people you know that I like to work with
the people that that are around me or
that are inspiring me as well like I
made some some show with my with my
boyfriend
to me and also is he working with
holography as well or is another media
no he's making he's making ceramics and
so what we did was we made a show
together where he exhibited his ceramics
and I exhibited my Holograms in the kind
of an installation together
and so that was really interesting it
was really material and
really immaterial yes yeah and it was it
was a really nice result I think um we
also have really different subjects some
matter as well so
[Applause]
it was like a boy Fantasy Versus girl
fantasy like he had all these battles
demon 's and stuff and I had all these
fairies and rainbows oh I see so that
was kind of
um the result of that one and yeah and I
I do make make a collaboration with
whoever is around not all I mean the the
reason that I have at the moment is a
collaboration also with four other
artists who are making rainbow Holograms
okay
an artist from
do you want to give their names yeah
Martina
um Mom Grover oh okay yeah she's um do
you know her the name I've never met her
oh okay see she's making Holograms in
Australia she's working at the rmit in
Melbourne and she she gave me a hologram
to to show in the exhibition of a boat
and um my friend yamo Hines is working
at the kahaim Academy of media arts and
he he made it a
portrait series of me so I'm using one
of those Holograms to exhibit okay and
then also there's a woman called Paul
and Nino rumors
and she made this beautiful rainbow
stereogram of this lorikeets from
Argentina
and then there's also a South Korean
artist called part two stop and he made
this kind of um Rainbow Cube for the
exhibition which is like a glass cube
with a with a rainbow hologram laminated
to the back of it so it looks
a large kind of
rainbow or something wow that's quite a
show yeah so it has um I it wasn't just
just my work that I included no it was
it was I wanted to include the works of
of my friends also well it does say Amy
rush and friends yeah
yeah well I mean you know it's it's nice
to it's nice to have friends sure
I had a a show with a gentleman the here
in this area of Pennsylvania and we both
put our work in this gallery
it was an artist that would take
three-dimensional objects and paint them
in such a way that they would look flat
and of course I did holography which is
essentially a flat plate which shows a
three-dimensional object so it was like
a flip side of a coin you would look at
his stuff and his three-dimensional
objects would go flat and you'd look at
my stuff and my two-dimensional plate
would go to 3D so it was very
complimentary yeah no I think it's
really nice to to to kind of bring it
bring it into a wider thing right
because you have your own way of working
but then there's so many other people in
the in the creates a kind of a visual
conversation and yeah I think it's
really interesting what are some of your
future plans do you plan on staying in
the field of holography or is this
something that you're touching on and
you
annual to some other type of media at
the point
um I'm not sure like I'm really
interested in trying to to incorporate
holography and you install in
installation like maybe with music or or
sculpture or
um
musical sculpture all kind of
kind of um
I would like to collaborate with
musicians okay to kind of create
holographic performance or something
like this like I really like making
these these
these kind of static images you know
that are not static because they're
moving but but I really I don't know
about just having it in a space you know
in a gallery kind of where everything is
hung one by one
more like to to work in Spec in a space
and interact with the space and kind of
um
created a more of a whole holistic
experience for the the people to to
enter okay yeah like I'm going to
Iceland in next month to make a a cave a
frozen ice cave wow with with Holograms
that are Frozen inside icicles oh my
goodness and also
um speakers that are Frozen inside
icicles and different
um LEDs that are Frozen inside icicles
and I want to install it inside a a real
ice cave wow and maybe work with some
local musicians to um to perform in
there also Bjork is from Iceland right
yes he is well there you go yeah I think
you know the funny thing is she's
actually performing in Australia while
we're gonna be in Iceland but
um maybe I mean I've actually met her
before once on an airplane no kidding I
was stuck it in in Spain
um I I lost my I didn't have my ticket
to go to New York or they wouldn't let
me on the plane because it was a one-way
one-way ticket
at the time where they were very very um
you can't enter the country if you don't
have a ticket out from there yes
yes and so I was actually at the airport
without being able to go on and I had to
borrow some money from
but you started to get a ticket to get
into New York wow
yes they were very kind that's my
daughter singing in the background can
you hear her she's singing kind of well
there you should I I'll send you a tape
of this and you'll have your music okay
maybe I can do that yeah a little baby
screaming in the ice cream
and how old is she she's going to she's
going to run in a couple of weeks oh
isn't that wonderful yeah good for you
yeah
I think this is
she really wants to be um out of the
gallery
she wants some fresh air yeah I think so
well it's nice to hear her in the
background because it makes it all more
human it is it's so hard for me to
picture like the other night when I was
finishing up the winter issue of that
hologram newsletter that I do I was
finishing up in between loads of laundry
yeah I came back down I thought you know
I can't picture anyone in holography
doing laundry I can only picture them
working in a lab or having exhibits but
we're all human we all do laundry we all
have families we all have all this that
uh
sometimes we never get to see The Human
Side of the people
who follow their work of
yeah I know I was talking with my
supervisor Paula Dawson about
um this artist Doris Villa yes and she
was telling me how how Doris wheeler was
creating her work
it's like
you know making five hour long kind of
EX I mean not not five hour long
exposures but multi-exposers over a
really long time that it kind of turned
into a perform
oh you know where she was like I don't
know it's a rumor like I have nothing to
back up this this maybe it's just a
fantasy I have about her working or
something but the way she would you know
go up and make this explosion explosion
down and cook dinner and then go up and
do another exposure but yeah I think it
has the same kind of the same Rhythm the
same everyday performance thing well
I want to wish you wish you the luck
thanks so much and good luck with your
tour which is New York
Iceland London and Germany
Germany what will you do after that go
back home I don't know I have to see
what happens okay my boyfriend lives in
I mean he's from France
I think he's going to convince me the
same sense that would be very nice well
it would be nice if you did speak French
oh I can't speak French oh neither can I
I have a hard time speaking English yes
you know oh that's nice all right you do
very well you have a very nice business
place oh thank you so much
okay all right will you take care of me
you too and thank you for taking the
time to come on to the show I'm sure
everybody's going to enjoy listening to
all the things you had to say so far oh
thank you so much it was really fun all
right thank you so much bye